<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="bread-cinnamon">
    <title>Cinnamon Rolls</title>
        <para><emphasis role="italic">
            a recipe from Cat Lookabaugh
        </emphasis></para>
    <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">In a large bowl, mix:</emphasis>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>3/4 cup butter</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>1 cup hot water</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">In a small bowl, mix:</emphasis>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>1/2 cup sugar</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>1 tsp salt</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>2 eggs <emphasis role="italic">(my recipe says
                        "slightly beaten" but I never beat them before
                        adding them) </emphasis>
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>1 cup cold water</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">In a cup measure, mix:</emphasis>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para> 2 packages dried yeast </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para> 1/4 cup luke-warm water </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para> Prepare cold mixture and then hot mixture. Combine hot and
        cold mixtures in the large bowl, and stir. Water should now be
        warm, so add the yeast mixture to it. </para>
    <para> Mix in approx. 7 cups of flour. These days I use self
        raising flour, but it works with regular flour too. As you're
        adding in the last cup or two of flour, you'll likely need to
        mix by hand. You want the dough to feel "doughy", which is to
        saying springy and not sticky. Do not over work it. </para>
    <para> Set bowl aside in warm place <emphasis role="italic">(we
            used to put on top of water heater)</emphasis>, covered by
        clean dish towel to rise. That'll take an hour or two. If you
        have time, you can punch down and let rise again. </para>
    <para> Now you're ready to play! Put some flour down on work
        surface, take out half the dough and start kneading, adding
        flour as needed. Again, don't add too much or the bread will
        be heavy and dense. </para>
    <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">Just Bread</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para> At this point, you can form into loaves and put into
        buttered loaf tins to bake as bread. Or you can roll in small
        balls (inch and a bit in diameter), and put three balls into
        each buttered muffin well to make dinner rolls. Either way,
        let it rise again in warm place. When ready, put in oven and
        bake for 25 minutes in 350 degree oven, or until golden brown. </para>
    <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">Cinnamon Rolls</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para> If you want to make the cinnamon rolls, see <emphasis
            role="bold">extra steps</emphasis> below to make the
        cinnamon sugar mix and prepare the pans for baking. Then, work
        your dough as described in the following paragraphs. </para>
    <para> Knead dough, as above. After you've finished kneading the
        dough, roll it out nice and thin <emphasis role="italic"
            >(maybe quarter of an inch thick)</emphasis>, into a
        basically rectangular shape. Spread with butter <emphasis
            role="italic">(I find melting butter and brushing it on
            works well. At least used softened butter!)</emphasis>.
        Now sprinkle on cinnamon sugar mixture <emphasis role="italic"
            >(which you've made in advance)</emphasis>, nice and thick
            <emphasis role="italic">(don't skimp on the
            filling)</emphasis>. Add chopped nuts if you like
            <emphasis role="italic">(pecans..yum!)</emphasis>. Roll
        the dough lengthwise into a long thin log <emphasis
            role="italic">(as opposed to a short thick
        one)</emphasis>. Cut into sections a couple of inches wide. </para>
    <para> You <emphasis role="italic">(having read these instructions
            before starting)</emphasis> took the time to prepare the
        cinnamon roll pans prior to rolling out the dough as shown in
        the extra steps. If not, do it now! </para>
    <para> Place the cut rolls into the pan, cut side down, three or
        four to a row. Don't cram them in too tight, since you want to
        let them rise again before baking. As you fill each pan, cover
        and put in warm place to rise. <emphasis role="italic">If you
            end up with just a few left, we've also baked in prepared
            pie pans. </emphasis></para>
    <para> Repeat process with remaining dough. </para>
    <para> When they've risen <emphasis role="italic">(maybe 30 or 45
            minutes)</emphasis>, bake in 350 degree oven about 25
        minutes or until golden brown. Place foil on a cooking rack,
        longer than the baking dish and tip the rolls out to cool.
        You'll want to put the dish in water quickly, cause the sticky
        goop hardens as it cools. <emphasis role="italic">Of course I
            like to scrape it up with a spoon and later suck it like a
            lollipop, but that's me!</emphasis> Or try to get the
        extra goop back on to the rolls <emphasis role="italic"
            >(easier said than done)</emphasis>. </para>
    <para> Delicious served warm <emphasis role="italic">(or
            reheated)</emphasis> with a bit of butter on top. To store
        for short term, put saran wrap on top, after they've cooled,
        and fold the tin foil up over edges. <emphasis role="italic"
            >Generally I refrigerate, but I think they're fine on the
            counter too.</emphasis> If you want to freeze a half batch
        for later, wrap whole foiled and saran wrapped package in yet
        more foil. </para>
    <warning>
    <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Dogs love these. One dog of mine
                took half a pan of cooled rolls right off the counter.
                She didn't even mind the spanking. She said it was
                totally worth it!</emphasis>
        </para>
    </warning>
    <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">Extra instructions for cinnamon
            rolls:</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
        <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">Cinnamon sugar
                mixture: </emphasis></emphasis></para>
    <para>
        <emphasis role="italic">This is where it gets fun, because I
            completely do this to taste. Haven't followed a recipe in
            eons. Word to the wise, use more cinnamon than you think
            you need. Lots more. </emphasis></para>
    <para> Basically, 2 parts white sugar to 1 part brown sugar. You
        should probably end up with at least a couple of cups when
        you're done. If you don't use it all, save it…works great for
        cinnamon toast, too. Add lots of cinnamon. Also a bit of
        nutmeg. <emphasis role="italic">I've even tossed in a splash
            of ginger.</emphasis> Mix together. <emphasis
            role="italic">If you want, let me know, and I'll go look
            up the actual proportions. </emphasis></para>
    <para>
        <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">Pan preparation:
            </emphasis></emphasis></para>
    <para> Take a couple of cake pans or glass casserole dishes and
        butter the bottoms and sides. Drizzle the bottom with Karo
        syrup. Don't cover it completely, since it will melt and
        spread as it heats up. Sprinkle more cinnamon sugar mix and
        chopped nuts over the whole bottom of the pan. </para>
</section>